Rhiannon: If a child or young person is
experiencing anxiety, there are things
that parents and carers can do to help.
Firstly, it's important to talk
to their child about their stress,
anxiety or worries and reassure them,
that their feelings are understood
and try to help them find solutions.
Leah: If the child is old enough, it
may help to explain what anxiety is and
the physical effects it has on the body.
It’s worthwhile trying to get a
child to recognise signs of anxiety
in themselves and encourage them to
learn to try to manage their anxiety
and ask for help when they need it.
Children of all ages find routines
reassuring, so sticking to regular
daily routines where possible can help
them to keep on top of their anxiety.
Rhiannon: If a child is worried about
something in particular, it’s best to
find solutions or plans to help them feel
that they can get through it, so that
their anxiety will not overwhelm them
and stop them doing things in the future.
Leah: If a child is anxious because
of distressing events, such as a
bereavement or family breakup, a parent
could look for books or films that
might help them in understanding their
feelings and help to discuss things
that happen and issues that arise.
Rhiannon: If a change is due to happen,
such as a house move, a child can be
prepared for the changes by talking
to them about what is going to happen
and looking at all the positives such
as choosing their decor, finding new
places to go, and trying to visit the
area and getting to know it in advance.
Leah: Distraction can be helpful for young
children, for example, if they are anxious
about something or going somewhere keep
them entertained on the way there, or give
them something new to get involved in.